Inventory of the Alfred Connor Bowman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alfred Connor Bowman papers
1943-1979
Bulk, 1945-1955
66015
Hoover Institution Archives
18 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 card file box, 1 motion picture film reel, 2 sound laquer discs (10.5 linear feet)
Diaries, speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, audio-visual materials, and photographs, relating to Allied Military occupation of Italy, especially Venezia Giulia and Trieste, after World War II, and plans for military occupation of North Korea in 1950.
Bowman, Alfred Connor, 1904-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1966.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1904 December 18 Born in Detroit, Michigan
1922-1924 Attended Wayne State University, Michigan
1926 Received JD from University of Michigan
1928 Married Claribel Pressnall
1931-1942 Admitted to California Bar and practiced in Los Angeles, California
1942 Commander Major in US Army in World War II
1943-1944 Chief, Liaison Division, Allied Control Commission for Italy
1944-1945 Regional Commissioner and Military Governor of the Emilia-Ramagna Region, Italy
1945-1947 Senior Civil Affairs Officer of Venezia Giulia, Italy
1953-1954 Chief Negotiation Commander of Military Armistice Committee for United Nations Command in Panmunjon, Korea
1955-1957 Chief of the Army Claims Division, Office of the Judge Advocate General (OTJAG); appointed to investigate 1947 Texas City Disaster
1963-1965 Participant in “First World Conference: World Peace Through Law”
1982 Published memoir, Zones of Strain: A Memoir of the Early Cold War
1982 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Alfred Connor Bowman papers contains reports, writings, research materials, correspondence, photographs, and audiovisual materials relating to Allied Military Government (AMG) occupation of the Venezia Giulia region of Italy, and, to a lesser extent, the initial United States operations in the Korean War.
The bulk of the collection is related to Bowman's career as a Senior Civil Affairs Officer and Military Governor for the AMG, and is comprised of declassified reports, criminal case files, correspondence, and press summaries relating to the socio-political climate of post-war Italy and amplified conflict between Italians and Yugoslavs. The collection also contains photographs and audiovisual materials detailing Bowman’s experiences in Italy. Also included are reports and news-clippings in regards to United States military intervention in Korea, located in the Korean War file. The Subject files and Speeches and Writings file detail Bowman’s post-war career with the United States military and materials that were used to publish his memoir, Zones of Strain: A Memoir of the Early Cold War.
The majority of the files in the collection retain their original folder titles.
United States. Army Officers.; Italy--History--Allied occupation, 1943-1947.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Military government.; Motion pictures.; Phonorecords.; Trieste (Italy)--History.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; Venezia Giulia (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1947); World War, 1939-1945--Territorial questions--Trieste.
- Biographical File, 1946-1979
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of diaries, correspondence, curriculum vitae, news clippings, and printed matter relating to Bowman's life, career as a lawyer, and participation with the American Bar Association. Arranged chronologically.
  - Diaries, 1944-1950
    - September 1944- June 1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - September 5, 1944-September 1, 1945 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - September 4, 1945-September 4, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - June 1946-June 1947 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - September 2, 1946-June 16, 1947 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Diary excerpt, October 1950 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - AMG biographical report, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Press mentions, 1946, 1957 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1961 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Trip to England, 1966 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - General correspondence, 1967-1978 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Peace Through Law European Conferences and American Bar Association, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 2: 6-7)
  - Interview of Alfred Bowman by Victoria Billings, Daily Breeze, 1974 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Fiftieth law school reunion, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Descriptions of medals received, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Speeches and Writings, 1947-1977
  Consists of speeches, published articles, a manuscript, and related research correspondence, articles, news clippings, and notes. Arranged by subject then chronologically.
  - Speeches, 1945-1957
    - Radio speeches in Venezia Giulia, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Farewell radio talk, 1947 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Speeches by others, 1947 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Civil Affairs and military government speeches, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Speeches made as Chief of Army Claims Division, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Speech given at the Pentagon, undated (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Writings, 1948-1951, undated
    - Research materials, news clippings, articles, and correspondence, 1946-1977 (Box-folder 3: 7; 4: 1-2)
    - "Partisan Disarmament," in Time magazine, May 10, 1948 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - "Venezia Giulia and Trieste: An address on the unique expression in Allied Military Government, delivered before Provisional Reserve Corps G-5 Section of the Military District of Washington," Military Government Journal, June 1948 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - "The Military Government Training Program," in The Army, Navy, Airforce Journal, April 1951 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Manuscript, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Allied Military Government File, 1943-1977
  Consists of correspondence, reports, memoranda, minutes, and printed matter relating to Senior Civil Affairs Office in Venezia Giulia. Includes declassified and public reports on domestic topics of the Venezia Giulia region and the Yugoslav and Italian conflict. Arranged by format.
  - Correspondence, 1945-1947
    Consists primarily of letters sent to the Senior Civil Affairs Office (SCAO).
    - Acknowledgement of letters sent to SCAO, 1945-1947
      - No. 94, June-August 1945 (Box-folder 5: 3)
      - No. 94D, November 1945 (Box-folder 5: 4)
      - No. 97A, September 1945 (Box-folder 5: 5)
      - No. 97B, September-October 1945 (Box-folder 5: 6)
      - No. 97C, October 1945 (Box-folder 6: 1)
      - No. 97F, February 1947 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - Correspondence from Foreign Policy Advisors (POLAD), 1946 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - General correspondence, December 1946- June 1947 (Box-folder 6: 4-8)
    - Letters of farewell, June 1947 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Reports, 1945-1947
    - Early History of Venezia Giulia, undated (Box 7)
    - History of AMG Venezia Giulia by Functional Subject, Volume I, Agriculture to Military, undated (Box 7)
    - "History of AMG Venezia Giulia by Functional Subject, Volume II, Partisans to Transportation,", undated (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
    - "History of AMG Venezia Giulia by Functional Subject, Volume III, Miscellaneous,", undated (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - "History of the Allied Military Government in Venezia Giulia,", undated (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Allied Forces reports and excerpts of agreements with Yugoslav Army, circa 1945 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - "Reports on reaction to the Separatist Tendency and Yugoslav Army and Organization in Zone 'B,'", 1945 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - Reports of proceedings at SCAO weekly press conference, 1945 November-1946 July (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - "Minutes of Meetings Held at Headquarters, AMG Venezia Giulia,", 1946 July 8- 1947 June 9 (Box-folder 9: 5; 10: 1)
    - "'Res Futura' A Compiled Political History of Zone 'A' of Venezia Giulia under Allied Military Government,", 1945-1947 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - "Labor Division Report: Historical Outline of Labor Division Activities from date of Allied Occupation (12 June 1945) to 'S' Day of the Italian Peace Treaty (10 February 1947),", circa 1947 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - General directives, Belgrade and Duino agreements, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - "The History of Monfalcone and District Communes," part I and II, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - "Prelude to Decision," report on Venezia Giulia under AMG, undated (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - "Outline of Economic Information on the Free Territory of Trieste," unofficial report, circa 1947 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Subject reports and notes on AMG in Venezia Giulia, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - "Principal Personalities,", 1946 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - AMG officers master lists, circa 1947 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Directories, undated (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - "History of Sesana,", 1947 (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - "Venezia Giulia Criminal Investigation Division Report on the Attempted Murder of Major Cunder Stane Yugoslav Army,", April 10, 1946 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    - "Case of Maria Pasquinelli,", 1947 (Box-folder 12: 1-2)
    - Maria Pasquinelli pardon, 1964,1977 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - Excerpt translation of "Sotto Due Bandiere,", undated (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Personal file, circa 1947 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - End of active duty in Venezia Giulia file, 1947 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - United States European Command (EUCOM), 1951 (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - Printed matter, 1945-1947
    - Military treaty booklets, programs, and ephemera, 1943-1947 (Box 13)
    - Amgothic Lines, and other outbursts of an uncivil affairs officer, 1943, 1945 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Poems, booklets, caricatures, and ephemera, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Italian Allied Military Occupation Stamp Collection, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - German surrender announcements in Star and Stripes, April-May 1945 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - The Emilia Way newsletters, 1945 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Press releases and news clippings, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - AMG Venezia Giulia proclamations and AMG Gazette, circa 1946 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - No. 603-616 Daily Press Summaries- Pro-Yugoslav, Pro-Italian, and Independent Press, 1947, July 11-26 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Maps, 1947 (Box-folder 15: 3)
- Korean War File, 1950-1953
  Consists of reports, orders, correspondence, agreements, and news clippings relating to Bowman's participation in the United States' effort to pass a resolution through the United Nation’s Security Council calling for military intervention in Korea and the subsequent cease-fire in 1953. Arranged chronologically.
  - Far East Command (FECOM) diary and news clippings, 1950 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Orders and correspondence, 1950 (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Proclamations and printed matter, 1950 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Souvenirs and news clippings, 1950 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - Extract of Korean War Crimes case reports addressed to United Nations, 1953 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - United Nations Command Military Armistice Commission (UNCMAC) agreements and negotiations, 1953 (Box-folder 16: 6)
- Subject File, 1952-1967
  Consists of reports, correspondence, news clippings, and ephemera relating to Bowman's post-World War II career with the Armed Forces. Arranged by subject.
  - Industrial College of the Armed Forces, 1952-1967 (Box-folder 17: 1-3)
  - Army Staff Judge Advocate office, 1949-1970 (Box-folder 17: 4-6)
  - Texas City Disaster investigation, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 18: 1-2)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1945-1947
  Includes images of the effects of war and Bowman's duties in Emilia and Venzia Giulia. Arranged by format.
  - San Marino, photographs, 1945 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - Bologna, Riccione, and Emilia region, Allied occupation, 1945 (Box-folder 18: 4-5)
  - Bowman's tour in Korea and honorary dinner at Stilwell Hall, Washington, D.C., 1950 (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - Emilia region occupation and Bowman press conferences, scrapbook, 1945 (Box 19)
  - Bretto di Sopra, album, 1946 (Box 19)
  - Reconstruction of San Daniele Del Carso, album, 1946-1947 (Box 20)
  - Trieste, album, circa 1947 (Box 20)
  - The Officers and Men of 13 Corps, AMG, album, circa 1947 (Box 20)
  - Negatives, unidentified, undated (Box 21)
- Audiovisual Material, 1946-1947
  Consists of a sound recording and a film.
  - Sound recordings
    - Farewell speech of Alfred Connor Bowman, sound laquer discs, 1946 July 23 (Record cabinet)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Use copy reference number: 66015_a_0002430
      Bowman describes Venezia Giulia and the activities of the occupation force.
  - Motion picture film
    - "Trieste 1945-47: large roll: Rebuilding, ETC of Baetto del soppa, small roll: police review and various other village rebuilding + openings Cine-Film Rolls," 16mm film, 650 ft. (Reel 1-2)